<!-- Begin introduction preface -->
<preface id="acknowledge">
<prefaceinfo>
<releaseinfo>$Id: preface.xml 48907 2013-07-11 07:31:43Z erik $</releaseinfo>
</prefaceinfo>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<para>
I want to acknowledge all of the people that helped review or edit the model 
documentation: David Lawrence, Samuel Levis, Keith Oleson, and Sean Swenson.  
Thank you for your help in catching errors, and making the document more 
understandable and readable. Our readers thank you as well, as now it is much
easier for them to digest. Any mistakes, or errors are all mine. If you run
across one of those errors, please let us know, by following 
<xref linkend="reporting_bugs"></xref>.
We also want to
thank the original authors of &ptclm;: Daniel M. Ricciuto, Dali Wang, Peter E. Thornton,
Wilfred M. Post, and R. Quinn Thomas for providing a nice addition to the &cesm; 
effort (included in previous versions of &cesm; including &cesm105; but NOT this 
release unfortunately, but planned for the next release). We also want to thank 
the folks at University of Michigan Biological Stations 
(US-UMB) who allowed us to use their Fluxnet station data and import it into our 
inputdata repository, especially Gil Bohrer the PI on record for this site
<!--
(see <xref linkend="AmeriFluxdata"></xref> for permission information on using this
data).
-->
</para>
</preface>

<preface id="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
The Community Land Model (&clmrel;) is the latest in a series of
global land models developed by the &cesm; Land Model Working Group
(<acronym>LMWG</acronym>) and maintained at the National Center for
Atmospheric Research (&ncar;). This guide is intended to instruct both
the novice and experienced user on running &clm;. This guide pertains to the
latest version &clmrel; available for download from the public release 
subversion repository as a part of &cesmrel;. Documentation may be different if you are using an
older version, you should either update to the latest version, or use the
documentation inside your own source tree. There is information in the 
<filename>ChangeLog</filename> file and in the <xref linkend="what_is_new"></xref>
regarding the changes from previous versions of &cesm;.
</para>

<para>
The novice user should read
<xref linkend="customize"></xref> in detail before beginning work, while the
expert user should read <xref linkend="what_is_new"></xref> and 
<xref linkend="quickstart"></xref> chapters, and then use the more detailed
chapters as reference. Before novice users go onto more technical problems covered
in <xref linkend="tools"></xref>, <xref linkend="adding_files"></xref>, <xref
linkend="special_cases"></xref>, or <xref linkend="single_point"></xref> they
should know the material covered in <xref linkend="customize"></xref> and be able
to replicate some of the examples given there. 
</para>
<para>
All users should read the 
<xref linkend="how_to"></xref>
and <xref linkend="help"></xref> sections to understand the document conventions
and the various ways of getting help on using &clm4;. Users should also read
the <xref linkend="whats_validated"></xref> section to see if their planned use of the
model is something that has been scientifically validated and well tested. Users
that are NOT using &ncar; machines or our list of well tested machines should also
read the <xref linkend="utilities_required"></xref> section to make sure they have
all the required UNIX utilities on the system they want to do their work.
</para>
<para>
Developers that are making changes to &clm; either for their own development or for 
development that they hope will eventually become a part of the main &clm; should
read the <xref linkend="testing"></xref> chapter. We have a suite of test scripts
that automatically test many different model configurations and namelist options,
as well as ensuring things like restarts are bit-for-bit and the like. It's helpful
to use these scripts to ensure your changes are working correctly. And it's far
easier to use the automated scripts rather than having to figure out, what to test,
how to do it, and then finally do it by hand. If you are using non supported machines
you may also want to use the test scripts to make sure your machine is working correctly.
</para>
</preface>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<preface id="doc_intro">
<title>Introduction to the &clm4; User's Guide</title>
<subtitle>What is in here anyway?</subtitle>

<para>
Here in the introduction we first give a simple guide to understand the document
conventions in <xref linkend="how_to"></xref>. The next section <xref linkend="what_is_new"></xref>
gives references to describe the differences between &clmrel; and previous &cesm; releases
both from a scientific as well as a software engineering point of view. For information on previous releases of &clm4;
before &clmcesm110; see the &cesm105; documentation.
The next section <xref linkend="quickstart"></xref>
is for users that are already experts in using &clm; and gives a quickstart guide to the 
bare details on how to use &clm4;. The next <xref linkend="whats_validated"></xref> tells
you about what has been extensively tested and scientifically validated (and maybe more
importantly) what has NOT. <xref linkend="utilities_required"></xref> lists the UNIX utilities
required to use &clm4; and is important if you are running on non-&ncar; machines, generic
local machines, or machines NOT as well tested by us at &ncar;. Next we
have <xref linkend="best_practice"></xref> to detail some of the best practices for using
&clm4; for science. The last introductory section is <xref linkend="help"></xref> which lists
different resources for getting help with &cesm1; and &clm4;.
</para>

<para>
<xref linkend="customize"></xref> goes into detail on how to setup and run simulations with
&clm4; and especially how to customize cases. Details of &setup;
modes and &buildnml; options as well as namelist options are given in this chapter. 
</para>

<para>
<xref linkend="tools"></xref> gives instructions on the &clm4; tools for creating input datasets
for use by &clm;, for the expert user. There's an overview of what each tool does, and some general notes on how to build 
the &FORTRAN; tools. Then each tool is described in detail along with different ways in
which the tool might be used.
A final section
on how to customize datasets for observational sites for very savvy expert users is given as the last section of this chapter.
</para>

<para>
As a followup to the tools chapter, <xref linkend="adding_files"></xref> tells how to add files to the
XML database for &buildnml; to use. This is important if you want to use the XML database to automatically select
user-created input files that you have created when you setup new cases with &clm;.
</para>

<para>
In <xref linkend="special_cases"></xref>, again for the expert user, we give details on how to do some particularly
difficult special cases. For example, we give the protocol for spinning up both the &clmcn; model and &clm; with dynamic
vegetation active (<acronym>CNDV</acronym>). We give instructions to do a spinup case
from a previous case with Coupler history output for atmospheric forcing. We also give 
instructions on running both the prognostic crop and irrigation models.
Lastly we tell the user how to use the DATM model to send historical &CO2; data to &clm;.
</para>

<para>
<xref linkend="single_point"></xref> outlines how to do single-point or
regional simulations using &clm4;.
This is useful to either compare &clm; simulations with point observational stations, 
such as tower sites (which might include your own atmospheric forcing), or
to do quick simulations with &clm; for example to test a new parameterization. There are
several different ways given on how to perform
single-point simulations which range from simple &PTSMODE; to more complex where you create all your own datasets, tying into
<xref linkend="tools"></xref> and also <xref linkend="adding_files"></xref> to add the
files into the &buildnml; XML database. The &ptclm; python script to run single-point simulations
was removed for this release (but is available in the previous &cesm105; release).
</para>

<para>
The next chapter, <xref linkend="trouble"></xref> gives some guidance on trouble-shooting
problems when using &clm4;. It doesn't cover all possible problems with &clm;, but gives
you some guidelines for things that can be done for some common problems.
</para>
<para>
In <xref linkend="testing"></xref> we go over the automated testing scripts for
validating that the &clm; is working correctly. The test scripts run many different
configurations and options with &clm; making sure that they work, as well as doing
automated testing to verify restarts are working correctly, and testing at many
different resolutions. In general this is an activity important only for a developer
of &clm;, but could also be used by users who are doing extensive code modifications
and want to ensure that the model continues to work correctly.
</para>

<para>
In the appendices we talk about some issues that are useful for advanced users and 
developers of &clm;.
</para>
<para>
Finally in <xref linkend="doc_build"></xref> we give instructions on how to build
the documentation associated with &clm; (i.e. how to build this document). This
document is included in every &clm; distribution and can be built so that you can
view a local copy rather than having to go to the &cesm; website. This also could
be useful for developers who need to update the documentation due to changes they
have made.
</para>

<!--
<sect1 id="listsofthings">
<title>List of Tables, Figures and Examples</title>

<sect2 id="lot">
<title>List of Tables</title>

<para>
List of tables in the document.
</para>
<lot id="listoftables">
<lotentry>Empty</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="table_required_files">Required Files<xref linkend="required_files"></xref></lotentry>
<lotentry pagenum="31">Page 31</lotentry>
<lotentry pagenum="57">Page 57</lotentry>
</lot>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="loe">
<title>List of Examples</title>
<para>
List of formal examples in the document.
</para>

<lot id="listofexamples">
<lotentry linkend="quickstart">Example of Running &clm4; on bluefire at 2-degree Resolution with Data Atmosphere Model</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="default_nml">Example of the Default Namelist</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="add_rm_primary_hist">Example of Namelist Adding and Removing Fields from the Primary History Files</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="add_aux_hist_chng_output_frq">Example of Namelist Add Auxiliary History Files and Change the Output History Frequency</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="rm_hist">Example of Namelist Removing All History Files</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="hist_averaging">Example of Namelist with Different Ways of Averaging on History Files</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="hist_vector">Example of Namelist Outputting History Fields as a 1D Vector</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="CN_SPINUP">Example of Doing a Spinup for CN</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="CNDV_SPINUP">Example of Doing a Spinup for CNDV</lotentry>
<lotentry linkend="DATM_CO2_TSERIES">Example of Sending Historical &CO2; Data from the Data Atmosphere Model</lotentry>
</lot>
</sect2>

</sect1>
-->

</preface>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->

<preface id="best_practice">
<title>Important Notes and Best Practices for Usage of &clm4;</title>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>When running with CN, it is critical to begin with initial conditions 
hat are provided with the release or to spin the model up following the CN spinup 
procedure before conducting scientific runs (see <xref linkend="CN_SPINUP"></xref>.  
Simulations without a proper spinup will effectively be starting from an unvegetated 
world. See <xref linkend="setting_finidat"></xref> for information on how to 
provide initial conditions for your simulation.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Initial condition files are provided for fully coupled BCN and offline 
ICN cases for 1850 and 2000 at finite volume grids: 1deg (0.9x1.25), 2deg (1.9x2.5), and T31 resolutions.  
We also have interpolated initial conditions for BCN for 1850 and 2000 for two finite volume
grids: 10x15, 4x5 and two HOMME grids (ne30np4 and ne120np4). There's also an
initial condition file for ICN with the prognostic crop model for 2000 at 2deg
resolution, and one with &clmsp; for 2000 at 2deg resolution. We also have initial
conditions for offline CNDV for 1850.
The 1850 initial condition files are in 'reasonable' equilibrium.  The 2000 initial condition files represent 
the model state for the year 2000, and have been taken from transient simulations.  
Therefore, by design the year 2000 initial condition files do not represent an 
equilibrium state.  Note also that spinning the 2000 initial conditions out to 
equilibrium will not reflect the best estimate of the real carbon/nitrogen state 
for the year 2000.  
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Users can generate initial condition files at different resolutions by 
using the &clm; tool <command>interpinic</command> to interpolate from one of the 
provided resolutions to the resolution of interest.  Interpolated initial condition 
files may no longer be in 'reasonable' equilibrium. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Aerosol deposition is a required field to &clm4; sent from the
atmosphere model.  Simulations without aerosol deposition will exhibit unreasonably 
high snow albedos. The model sends aerosol deposition from the atmospheric model (either 
&cam; or &datm;). When running with prescribed aerosol the atmosphere
model will interpolate the aerosols from 2-degree resolution to the resolution the 
atmosphere model is running at.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</preface>


<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<preface id="how_to">
<prefaceinfo>
<itermset>
   <indexterm zone="how_to" id="EDITOR"><primary>$EDITOR</primary></indexterm>
</itermset>
</prefaceinfo>

<title>How to Use This Document</title>
<subtitle>Conventions used in the document for code and commands</subtitle>

<para>
This section provides the details in using &clm; with the &cesm; modeling
system. Links to descriptions and definitions have been provided in the code below.
We use the same conventions used in the &cesm; documentation as outlined below.
</para>

<screen width="99">
Throughout the document this style is used to indicate shell
commands and options, fragments of code, namelist variables, etc.
Where examples from an interactive shell session are presented, lines
starting with > indicate the shell prompt.  A backslash "\" at the end
of a line means the line continues onto the next one (as it does in
standard UNIX shell).  Note that $EDITOR" is used to refer to the 
text editor of your choice. $EDITOR is a standard UNIX environment 
variable and should be set on most UNIX systems. Comment lines are 
signaled with a "#" sign, which is the standard UNIX comment sign as well.
$CSMDATA is used to denote the path to the inputdata directory for
your &cesm; data. 

> This is a shell prompt with commands \
that continues to the following line.
> $EDITOR filename # means you are using a text editor to edit "filename"
# This is a comment line

</screen>

</preface>


<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<preface id="what_is_new">
<title>What is new with &clmrel; since previous public releases?</title>
<para>
In this section we list the updates that have occurred to &clm4; since previous
public releases of &cesm;. 
The &cesm112; 
<ulink url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.1/notable_improvements.html">Notable Improvements</ulink>
page gives a synopsis of the changes to all &cesm; components since the &cesm1; release. See
<ulink url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.1/notable_improvements.html#CLM">the &clm; section</ulink>
for changes particular for &clm;. More details are given in the 
<ulink url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.1/clm/models/lnd/clm/doc/ChangeLog">&clm; ChangeLog file</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
Previous release pages give similar list of changes for previous
versions of the model. The 
<ulink url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.0/clm/models/lnd/clm/doc/UsersGuide/book1.html">&clmcesm105; User's Guide </ulink>
gives information on the updates for versions up to &clmcesm105;.
</para>

</preface>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<preface id="quickstart">
<title>Quickstart to using &clm4;</title>
<para>
Before working with &clm4; read the QuickStart Guide in the
<ulink url="&cesmwebmodelrel;cesm">&cesmrel;
Scripts User's Guide</ulink>. Once you are familiar with how to setup cases for 
any type of simulation with &cesm; you will want to direct your attention to the specifics
of using &clm;.
</para>
<para>
For some of the details of setting up cases for &clm4; read the README and text files available
from the "models/lnd/clm/doc" directory (see the "&clm; Web pages" section for a link to the list
of these files). Here are the important ones that you should be familiar with.
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><ulink url="../README">README</ulink> file describing the directory structure.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="../Quickstart.userdatasets">Quickstart.userdatasets</ulink> file describing how to
use your own datasets in the model (also see <xref linkend="own_single_point_datasets"></xref>).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>&KnownBugs; file describing known
problems in &clm4; (that we expect to eventually fix).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>&KnownLims; file 
describing known limitations in &clm4; and workarounds that we do NOT expect to
fix.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
<para>The <emphasis>IMPORTANT_NOTES</emphasis> file talks about important things
for users to know about using the model scientifically. It content is given in 
the next chapter on "<xref linkend="whats_validated"></xref>".
</para>
<para>The <emphasis>ChangeLog/ChangeSum</emphasis> talk about advances in different
versions of &clm;. The content of these files is largely explained in the previous 
chapter on "<xref linkend="what_is_new"></xref>".</para>
<para>
Note other directories have README files that explain different components and tools used
when running &clm; and are useful in
understanding how those parts of the model work and should be consulted when using tools in those directories.
For more details on configuring and customizing a case with &clm; see <xref linkend="customize"></xref>.
</para>
<para>The <emphasis>Quickstart.GUIDE</emphasis> (which can be found in
<filename>models/lnd/clm/doc)</filename> is repeated here.</para>
<programlisting width="99">
&quickstart_guide;
</programlisting>
</preface>
<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<preface id="whats_validated">
<title>What is scientifically validated and functional in &clmrel;?</title>
<para>
In this section we go over what has been extensively tested and scientifically validated
with &clm4;, and maybe more importantly what has NOT been tested and may NOT be
scientifically validated. You can use all features of &clm;, but need to realize that
some things haven't been tested extensively or validated scientifically. When you use
these features you may run into trouble doing so, and will need to do your own work to
make sure the science is reasonable.
</para>

<sect1 id="standard_validated">
<title>Standard Configuration and Namelist Options that are Validated</title>
<para>
In this release "NO" standard configuration are scientifically validated. Changes to the science of the
model are minimul since &cesm105; so we expect answers to be very similar to using it.
</para>
<para>
In the sections below we go through configuration and/or namelist options or modes that the user should be especially wary of using. You
are of course free to use these options, and you may find that they work functionally. Although in some cases you will find issues even
with functionality of using them. If so you will need to test, debug and find solutions for these issues on your own. But in every case 
you will need to go through more extensive work to validate these options from a scientific standpoint.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="config_not_validated">
<title>Configure Modes NOT scientifically validated, documented, supported or, in some
cases,  even advised to be used:</title>
<para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
   <para>
   <varname>C13</varname><screen>(-c13)</screen>
The C13 mode for bgc=cn is NOT scientifically validated or documented and is NOT 
recommended for use. It is also deprecated and will be removed in the next release 
(although &clm45; will have namelist options for both C13 and C14).
   </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
   <para>
   <varname>SNICAR_FRC</varname><screen>(-snicar_frc)</screen>
       This mode is tested and functional, but is NOT constantly scientifically validated, and should be 
       considered experimental.
   </para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="nml_not_validated">
<title>Namelist options that should NOT be exercised:</title>
<sect2 id="bld_nml_not_validated">
<title>Build-Namelist options that should NOT be exercised:</title>
<para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>-irrig with -bgc cn</emphasis>
We have only run the irrigation model with &clmsp; (i.e. without the CN model). We
recommend that if you want to run the irrigation model with CN, that you do a spinup.
But, more than that you may need to make adjustments to
<varname>irrig_factor</varname> in
<filename>models/lnd/clm/src/biogeophys/CanopyFluxesMod.F90</filename>. See the
notes on this in the description of the irrigation model in the
<ulink url="&cesmwebmodelrel;/CLMcropANDirrigTechDescriptions.pdf">
Technical Descriptions of the Interactive Crop Management and Interactive
Irrigation Models</ulink>.
   </para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>-irrig with -crop on</emphasis>
Irrigation doesn't work with the prognostic crop model. Irrigation is only applied to 
generic crop currently, which negates it's practical usage.  We also have a known 
problem when both are on (see bug 1326 in the &KnownBugs; file).
If you try to run in this mode, the &clm; &buildnml; will return with an error.
   </para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>-lnd_res:</emphasis>  Fine-mesh mode, functional, but experimental</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>-rcp:</emphasis>  Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP)
for future scenarios, functional for limited resolutions, but experimental</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>-datm_*:</emphasis>  All options that start with "datm_" they are
only used for &clm; stand-alone testing.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>-drv_*:</emphasis>  All options that start with "drv_" they are
only used for &clm; stand-alone testing.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="nml_items_not_validated">
<title>Namelist items that should NOT be exercised:</title>
<para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
   <para>
   <emphasis>suplnitro='ALL'</emphasis>
       The suplnitro namelist option to the CN Biogeochemistry model supplies
unlimited nitrogen and therefore vegetation is over-productive in this mode.
   </para>

</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>urban_traffic:</emphasis>         Not currently functional</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</preface>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<preface id="utilities_required">
<title>What are the UNIX utilities required to use &clm;?</title>
<para>
Running the &clm; requires a suite of UNIX utilities and programs and you should
make sure you have all of these available before trying to go forward with using
it. If you are missing one of these you should contact the systems administrator
for the machine you wish to run on and make sure they are installed.
<simplelist>
<member>List of utilities required for &cesm; in the "&cesmrel; Software/Operating System Prerequisites" section
in <ulink url="&cesmwebmodelrel;/cesm/doc/usersguide/book1.html">&cesmwebmodelrel;/cesm/doc/usersguide/book1.html</ulink></member>
<member>UNIX bash shell (for some of the &clm; tools scripts)</member>
<member>&ncl; (for some of the offline tools for creating/modifying &clm; input
datasets see <xref linkend="tools"></xref> for more information on &ncl;)</member>
<member>Python (optional, needed for &ptclm;)</member>
<member>xsltproc, docbook and docbook utilities (optional, needed to build the Users-Guide)</member>
<member>protex and latex2html (optional, needed to build the Code-Reference Guide)</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
</preface>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<preface id="help">
<prefaceinfo>
<itermset>
  <indexterm zone="CESM_BB"><primary>&cesm; Online Bulletin Board</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm zone="CESM_UG"><primary>&cesmrel; Scripts User's Guide</primary></indexterm>
</itermset>
</prefaceinfo>
<title>Other resources to get help from</title>

<para>
In addition to this users-guide there are several other resources that are available
to help you use &clm4;. The first one is the &cesmrel; User's-Guide, which documents the entire
process of creating cases with &cesmrel;. The next is the &cesm; bulletin board which is 
a web-site for exchanging information between users of &cesm;. There are also &clm;
web-pages specific for &clm;, and finally there is an email address to report bugs that
you find in &cesmrel;.
</para>

<sect1 id="CESM_UG">
<title>The &cesm; User's-Guide</title>
<para>
&clmrel; is always run from within the standard &cesmrel; build and run scripts. Therefore, the
user of &clm4;
should familiarize themselves with the &cesmrel; scripts and understand how to work with them.
User's-Guide documentation on the &cesmrel; scripts are available from the following web-page. The purpose
of this &clmrel; User's Guide is to give the &clm4; user more complete details on how to work
with &clm; and the set of tools that support &clm;, as well as to give examples that are unique to the use
of &clm;. However, the &cesmrel; Scripts User's-Guide remains the primary source to get detailed
information on how to build and run the &cesm; system.
<simplelist>
<member><ulink url="&cesmwebmodelrel;/sm/doc/usersguide/book1.html">cesmrel; Scripts
User's-Guide (&cesmwebmodelrel;/cesm/doc/usersguide/book1.html)</ulink></member>
</simplelist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="CESM_BB">
<title>The &cesm; Bulletin Board</title>
<para>
There is a rich and diverse set of people that use the &cesm;, and often it is useful to be in contact with
others to get help in solving problems or trying something new. To facilitate this we have an online
Bulletin Board for questions on the &cesm;. There are also different sections in the Bulletin Board for
the different component models or for different topics.
<simplelist>
<member><ulink url="http://bb.cgd.ucar.edu/">&cesm; Online Bulletin Board</ulink></member>
</simplelist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="CLM_web">
<title>The &clm; web pages</title>
<para>
The main &clm; web page contains information on the &clm;, it's history, developers, as well as
downloads for previous model versions. There are also documentation text files in the 
models/lnd/clm/doc directory that give some quick information on using &clm;.
<simplelist>
<member><ulink url="http://www.cgd.ucar.edu/tss/clm/">&clm; web page</ulink></member>
<member><ulink url="../">&clm; Documentation Text Files</ulink></member>
</simplelist>
Also note that several of the XML database files can be viewed in a web browser to get
a nice table of namelist options, namelist defaults, or compsets. Simply view them
as a local file and bring up one of the following files:
<simplelist>
<member><ulink
url="../../bld/namelist_files/namelist_definition.xml">models/lnd/clm/bld/namelist_files/namelist_definition.xml</ulink>
-- definition of &clm; namelist items.</member>
<member><ulink
url="../../bld/namelist_files/namelist_defaults_clm.xml">models/lnd/clm/bld/namelist_files/namelist_defaults_clm.xml</ulink>
-- default values for &clm; namelist items.</member>
<member><ulink
url="../../../../../scripts/ccsm_utils/Case.template/config_definition.xml">scripts/ccsm_utils/Case.template/config_definition.xml</ulink>
-- definition of all <filename>env_*.xml</filename> items.</member>
<member><ulink
url="../../../../../scripts/ccsm_utils/Case.template/config_compsets.xml">scripts/ccsm_utils/Case.template/config_compsets.xml</ulink>
-- definition of all the compsets.</member>
<member><ulink
url="../../bld/namelist_files/history_fields.xml">models/lnd/clm/bld/namelist_files/history_fields.xml</ulink>
-- definition of &clm; history fields.</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="reporting_bugs">
<title>Reporting bugs in &clm4;</title>
<para>
If you have any problems, additional questions, bug reports, or any other feedback, please send an email to
<email>cesmhelp@cgd.ucar.edu</email>. If you find bad, wrong, or misleading information
 in this users guide send an email to <email>erik@ucar.edu</email>. The current list of
known issues for &clmrel; is in the &KnownBugs; file, and the list of issues for
&cesmrel; is at... 
<ulink url="&cesmwebmodelrel;/tags/cesm1_1_1/#PROBLEMS">
&cesmwebmodelrel;/tags/cesm1_1_1/#PROBLEMS
</ulink>.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="acronymns">
<title>Some Acronymn's We'll be Using</title>
<para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>&cam;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="CAM"></anchor>
Community Atmosphere Model (&cam;)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&cesm;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="CESM"></anchor>
Community Earth System Model (&cesm;)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&clm;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="CLM"></anchor>
Community Land Model (&clm;)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&clmcn;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="CLMCN"></anchor>
Community Land Model (&clm;) with Carbon Nitrogen (CN) Biogeochemistry
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&clmsp;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="CLMSP"></anchor>
Community Land Model (&clm;) with Satellite Phenology (SP)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&clmu;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="CLMU"></anchor>
Community Land Model (&clm;) Urban Model
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&datm;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="DATM"></anchor>
Data Atmosphere Model (&datm;)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&esmf;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="ESMF"></anchor>
Earth System Modelling Framework
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&ncar;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="NCAR"></anchor>
National Center for Atmospheric Research
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&ptclm;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="PTCLM"></anchor>
PoinT &clm;
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>&scrip;</term><listitem> 
<para>
<anchor id="SCRIP"></anchor>
Spherical Coordinate Remapping and Interpolation Package (&scrip;)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</sect1>

</preface>



<!-- End introduction preface -->
