<!-- Beg of special cases chapter -->
<chapter id="special_cases">
<title>How to run some special cases</title>
<para>
In this chapter we describe how to run some special cases that take more than one step
to do. The straightforward cases have compsets and/or build-namelist use-cases setup for
them or require simple editing of a single-case. All of the cases here require you
to do at least two simulations with different configurations, or require more complex
editing of the case (changing the streams files).
</para>
<para>
The nine cases we will describe are:
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Running with the prognostic crop model on</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Running with the irrigation model on</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Spinning up the Satellite Phenology Model (&clmsp; spinup)</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Spinning up the biogeochemistry Carbon-Nitrogen Model (CN spinup)</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Spinning up the Carbon-Nitrogen Dynamic Global Vegetation Model (CNDV spinup)</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Running with MOAR data as atmospheric forcing to spinup the model</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Running with your own previous simulation as atmospheric forcing to spinup the model</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Doing perturbation error growth tests</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Running stand-alone &clm; with transient historical &CO2;
concentration</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
<caution>
<para>
The cases in this chapter are more sophisticated and require more technical knowledge
and skill than cases in previous chapters. The user should be very familiar with doing
simple cases before moving onto the cases described here.
</para>
</caution>
<sect1 id="CROP">
<title>Running with the prognostic crop model on</title>

<para>
In &clmcesm103; a prognostic crop model was added to &clm4;. The prognostic crop
model is setup to work with CN for present day conditions and we have surface
and initial condition datasets at f19 resolution. In order to use the initial condition
file, we need to set the <envar>RUN_TYPE</envar> to <literal>startup</literal> rather
than <literal>hybrid</literal> since the compset for f19 sets up to use an initial
condition file without crop active. To activate the crop model we simply add "-crop on"
to &CLMCONFIG;.
<example>
<title>Example Crop Simulation</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case CROP -res f19_g16 -compset ICN -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd CROP
# Append "-crop on" to &CLMCONFIG; in env_build.xml (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange &CLMCONFIG;="-crop on" -append
# Change to startup type so uses spunup initial conditions file for crop if it exists
# By default the model will do a hybrid startup with an initial condition file
# incompatible with the crop surface dataset.
> ./xmlchange RUN_TYPE=startup
> ./cesm_setup
# Now build and run normally
> ./CROP.build
> ./CROP.submit
</screen>
</example>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="IRRIG">
<title>Running with the irrigation model on</title>

<para>
In &clmcesm103; an irrigation model for generic crop was added to &clm4;. Currently,
irrigation and crop can NOT be used together see bug number 1326 in the 
&KnownBugs; file.
The irrigation model is tuned to work only with &clmsp; see the caution below for
for more information on this. To turn on
irrigation we simply add "-irrig on" to &CLMBLDNML;. Just as in the crop example we
also change <envar>RUN_TYPE</envar> to <literal>startup</literal> so that we don't use
an initial condition file that is incompatible with irrigation.
<example>
<title>Example Irrigation Simulation</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
# Note here we do a &clmsp; simulation as that is what has been validated
> ./create_newcase -case IRRIG -res f19_g16 -compset I -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd IRRIG
# Append "-irrig" to &CLMBLDNML; in env_run.xml (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange &CLMBLDNML;="-irrig" -append
# Change to startup type so uses spunup initial conditions file for irrigation if it exists
# By default the model will do a hybrid startup with an initial condition file
# incompatible with the irrigation surface dataset.
> ./xmlchange RUN_TYPE=startup
> ./cesm_setup
# Now build and run normally
> ./IRRIG.build
> ./IRRIG.submit
</screen>
</example>
<caution>
<para>
We have only run the irrigation model with &clmsp; (i.e. without the CN model). We 
recommend that if you want to run the irrigation model with CN, that you do a spinup 
as outlined in the examples below. But, more than that you may need to make 
the adjustments we discuss in <xref linkend="bld_nml_not_validated"></xref>.
</para>
</caution>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="CLMSP_SPINUP">
<title>Spinning up the Satellite Phenology Model (&clmsp; spinup)</title>

<para>
To spin-up the &clmsp; model you merely need to run &clmsp; for 50 simulation
years starting from arbitrary initial conditions. You then use the final
restart file for initial conditions in other simulations.
Because, this is a straight forward operation we will NOT give
the details on how to do that here, but leave it as an exercise for the reader.
See the <xref linkend="final_CN_spinup"></xref> as an example of doing this
as the last step for &clmcn;.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="CN_SPINUP">
<title>Spinning up the biogeochemistry Carbon-Nitrogen Model (CN spinup)</title>
<para>
To get the &clmcn; model to a steady state, you first run it from arbitrary initial conditions
using the "accelerated decomposition spinup" (-spinup AD in &clm; &configure;) mode for 600 simulation years. After
this you branch from this mode in the "exit spinup" (-spinup exit in &clm; &configure;), run
for a simulation year, and then save a restart from that and use it as initial conditions 
for further spinup of CN (at least 50 simulation years).
</para>
<procedure>
<title>Spinup of &clmcn;</title>
<step>
<title>AD_SPINUP</title>
<para>
For the first step of running 600 years in "-spinup AD" mode, you will setup
a case, and then edit the values in <filename>env_build.xml</filename> and
<filename>env_run.xml</filename> so that the right configuration is turned on and
the simulation is setup to run for the required length of simulation time.
So do the following:
<example>
<title>Example AD_SPINUP Simulation</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case CN_spinup -res f19_g16 -compset ICN -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd CN_spinup
# Append "-spinup AD" to &CLMCONFIG;
> ./xmlchange &CLMCONFIG;="-spinup AD" -append
# The following sets &CLMFORCECOLD; to "on" (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange &CLMFORCECOLD;=on
# Make the output history files only annual, by adding the following to the &usernlclm; namelist
> echo 'hist_nhtfrq = -8760' >> &usernlclm;
# Now setup
> ./cesm_setup -case
# Now build
> ./CN_spinup.build
# The following sets RESUBMIT to 30 times in env_run.xml (you could also use an editor)
# The following sets STOP_DATE,STOP_N and STOP_OPTION to Jan/1/601, 20, "nyears" in env_run.xml (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange RESUBMIT=30,STOP_N=20,STOP_OPTION=nyears,STOP_DATE=6010101
# Now run normally
> ./CN_spinup.submit
</screen>
</example>
Afterwards save the last restart file from this simulation to use in the next step.
</para>
</step>

<step>
<title>EXIT_SPINIP</title>
<para>
<example>
<title>Example EXIT_SPINUP Simulation</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case CN_exitspinup -res f19_g16 -compset ICN -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd CN_exitspinup
# Append "-spinup exit" to &CLMCONFIG;
> ./xmlchange &CLMCONFIG;="-spinup exit" -append
# Change run type to branch and branch from the last year of the last simulation
> ./xmlchange RUN_TYPE=branch,RUN_REFCASE=CN_spinup,RUN_REFDATE=0601-01-01,GET_REFCASE=FALSE
> ./cesm_setup
# Go ahead and build, so that the run directory is created
> ./CN_exitspinup.build
# Now, Copy the last restart files from the earlier case into your run directory
> cp /ptmp/$LOGIN/archive/CN_spinup/rest/CN_spinup.*.r*.0601-01-01-00000* /ptmp/$LOGIN/CN_exitspinup
# And copy the rpointer files for datm and drv from the earlier case
> cp /ptmp/$LOGIN/archive/CN_spinup/rest/rpointer.atm /ptmp/$LOGIN/CN_exitspinup
> cp /ptmp/$LOGIN/archive/CN_spinup/rest/rpointer.drv /ptmp/$LOGIN/CN_exitspinup
# The following sets STOP_OPTION to "nyears" in env_run.xml (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange STOP_OPTION=nyears,STOP_N=1
# Now run normally
> ./CN_exitspinup.submit
</screen>
</example>
</para>
</step>

<step>
<title>Final spinup</title>
<para>
Next save the last restart file from this step and use it as the "finidat" file to
use for one more spinup for at least 50 years in normal mode. 
So do the following:
<example id="final_CN_spinup">
<title>Example Final CN Spinup Simulation</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case CN_finalspinup -res f19_g16 -compset ICN -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd CN_finalspinup
# The following sets &CLMFORCECOLD; to "on" in env_build.xml (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange &CLMFORCECOLD;=on
# Now, Copy the last &clm; restart file from the earlier case into your run directory
> cp /ptmp/$LOGIN/archive/CN_exitspinup/rest/CN_exitspinup.clm*.r*.0602-01-01-00000.nc \
/ptmp/$LOGIN/CN_finalspinup
# And copy the rpointer files for datm and drv from the earlier case
> cp /ptmp/$LOGIN/archive/CN_exitspinup/rest/rpointer.atm /ptmp/$LOGIN/CN_finalspinup
> cp /ptmp/$LOGIN/archive/CN_exitspinup/rest/rpointer.drv /ptmp/$LOGIN/CN_finalspinup
# Set the finidat file to the last restart file saved in previous step
> echo ' finidat = "CN_exitspinup.clm2.r.0602-01-01-00000.nc"' > &usernlclm;
# Now setup
> ./cesm_setup
> $EDITOR Buildconf/clm.buildnml.csh
> Now build
> .CN_finalspinup.build
# The following sets RESUBMIT to 5 times in env_run.xml (you could also use an editor)
# The following sets STOP_N and STOP_OPTION to 10 and "nyears" in env_run.xml (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange RESUBMIT=5,STOP_OPTION=nyears,STOP_N=10
> Now run as normal
> .CN_finalspinup.submit
</screen>
</example>
</para>
<para>
To assess if the model is spunup plot trends of CN variables of interest. If you see
a trend, you may need to run the simulation longer.
Finally save the restart file from the end of this simulation to use as an "finidat" file for future
simulations.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="CNDV_SPINUP">
<title>Spinning up the Carbon-Nitrogen Dynamic Global Vegetation Model (CNDV spinup)</title>
<para>
To spinup the &clm; CNDV model -- you first follow the procedures above to spinup the CN model.
Then you take the CN initial state file you created for the spinup with just CN, and 
run CNDV for 200 more years. 
We've provided such spunup files for two resolutions (f09 and f19) and two time-periods 
(1850 and 2000), so in this example we will use the files provided to start from.
We've also provided a spinup file at f19 resolution for CNDV, hence the following is
NOT required when running at f19.
If you were to start from your own &clmcn; spunup files -- the procedure would require
some modification.
There are no compsets using CNDV, so in
<filename>env_build.xml</filename> change <envar>CLM_CONFIG_OPTS</envar> to
<literal>-bgc cndv</literal>.
<example>
<title>Example CNDV Spinup Simulation</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case CNDV_spinup -res f09_g16 -compset ICN -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd CNDV_spinup
# Set run type to startup and do a cold start and CLM_CONFIG_OPTS to CNDV
> ./xmlchange RUN_TYPE=startup,CLM_CONFIG_OPTS="-bgc cndv"
# Make the default primary history file annual and add an annual 1D vector auxiliary file
# By putting the following in a &usernlclm; file.
> cat &lt;&lt; EOF >> &usernlclm;
 hist_nhtfrq = -8760, -8760
 hist_mfilt  =     1, 1
 hist_fincl2 = 'TLAI', 'TSAI', 'HTOP', 'HBOT', 'NPP'
 hist_dov2xy = .true., .false.
> ./cesm_setup
# NOTE: If you were using your own CN spinup files you would edit the namelist to use it
# $EDITOR Buildconf/clm.buildnml.csh
#
# Now build and run as normal
> ./CNDV_spinup.build
# The following sets RESUBMIT to 10 times, STOP_N/STOP_OPTION to 20 years in env_run.xml (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange RESUBMIT=10,STOP_OPTION=nyears,STOP_N=20
# Make sure you turn archiving on, so you save your files to long term archival
> ./xmlchange DOUT_L_MS=TRUE
> ./CNDV_spinup.submit
</screen>
</example>

</para>
<para>
In a data analysis tool you should examine the auxiliary file and examine the
<varname>pfts1d_wtgcell</varname> to see where and what types of vegetation have
been established. See the caution in <xref linkend="vector1D"></xref> for more
information on visualizing and analyzing 1D vector fields.
</para>
<note>
<para>
CNDV also writes out two vector fields to "hv" auxiliary files, on an annual basis by
default.
</para>
</note>
<note>
<para>
We've provided a spinup file for CNDV at f19 resolution, you could also use
<command>interpinic</command> to interpolate this file to other resolutions.
</para>
</note>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="MOARFORCE">
<title>Running with MOAR data as atmospheric forcing to spinup the model</title>
<para>
Because it takes so long to spinup the CN model (as we just saw previously), if you 
are doing fully coupled simulations with active atmosphere and ocean, you will want 
to do the spinup portion of this "offline". So instead of doing expensive fully 
coupled simulations for the spinup duration, you run &clm; in a very cheap "I" 
compset using atmospheric forcing from a shorter fully coupled simulation 
(or a simulation run previously by someone else).
</para>
<para>
In this example we will use the <literal>I1850SPINUPCN</literal> compset to setup
&clm; to run with atmospheric forcing from a previous fully coupled simulation with
data that is already stored on disk on yellowstone. There are several simulations that
have high frequency data for which we can do this. You can also do this on a machine
other than yellowstone, but would need to download the data from the Earth System Grid and
change the datapath similar to <xref linkend="ownforce"></xref>. 
<example>
<title>Example Simulation with MOAR Data on yellowstone</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case MOARforce1850 -res f19_g16 -compset I1850SPINUPCN -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd MOARforce1850
# The following sets the casename to point to for atm forcing (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange DATM_CPL_CASE=b40.1850.track1.1deg.006a
# The following sets the align year and years to run over for atm forcing 
#  (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange DATM_CPL_YR_ALIGN=1,DATM_CPL_YR_START=960,DATM_CPL_YR_END=1030
> ./cesm_setup
# Now build and run as normal
> ./MOARforce1850.build
> ./MOARforce1850.submit
</screen>
</example>
<caution>
<para>
Because of bug 1339 (see the &KnownBugs; file on this) 
you can't run with 83 or more years of forcing. If you do need to run with more years of 
forcing, you'll need to address the issue as outlined in the &KnownBugs; file.
</para>
</caution>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="OWNCPLHISTFORCE">
<title>Running with your own previous simulation as atmospheric forcing to spinup the model</title>
<para>
Another way that you might want to spinup the model is to run your own simulation 
for a relatively short period (either a B, E, or F compset) and then use it as forcing 
for your "I" case later. By only running 20 to 50 years for the fully coupled case,
you'll save a substantial amount of computer time rather than running the entire spinup
period with a fully coupled model.
</para>
<para>
The first thing we need to do is to run a fully coupled case and save the atmospheric
coupling fields on a three hourly basis. In this example, we will run on yellowstone
and archive the data to a local disk that we can then use in the next simulation.
<example>
<title>Example Fully Coupled Simulation to Create Data to Force Next Example Simulation</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case myBCN1850 -res f09_g16 -compset B1850CN  -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd myBCN1850
> ./cesm_setup
# Set histaux_a2x3hr to .true. in your user_nl_cpl output from the atmosphere model 
# will be saved 3 hourly
echo "histaux_a2x3hr=.true." >> user_nl_cpl
# Now build
> ./myBCN1850.build
# The following sets the archival disk space (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange DOUT_S_ROOT='/glade/home/$USER/$CASE'
# Make sure files are archived to disk, but NOT to long term storage 
# (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange DOUT_S=TRUE,DOUT_L_MS=FALSE
# Set the run length to run a total of 20 years (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange RESUBMIT=9,STOP_OPTION=nyears,STOP_N=2
# Now run as normal
> ./myBCN1850.submit
</screen>
</example>
<caution>
<para>
Because of bug 1733 (see the &KnownBugs; file on this) you'll need to edit the driver
code in order for it to produce the correct list of fields needed to run the model
later.
</para>
</caution>
</para>
<para>
Now we run an I compset forced with the data from the previous simulation using
the &CPLHIST; option to DATM_MODE. See 
<xref linkend="cplhist_mode_datm_settings"></xref> for more information on the
&datm; settings for &CPLHIST; mode.
<example id="ownforce">
<title>Example Simulation Forced with Data from the Previous Simulation</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case frcwmyBCN1850 -res f09_g16 -compset I1850SPINUPCN -mach yellowstone_intel
> cd frcWmyBCN1850
# The following sets the casename to point to for atm forcing (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange DATM_CPLHIST_CASE="myBCN1850"
# The following sets the align year and years to run over for atm forcing 
#  (you could also use an editor)
> ./xmlchange DATM_CPLHIST_YR_ALIGN="1",DATM_CPLHIST_YR_START=1,DATM_CPLHIST_YR_END=20
# Set the strm_datdir in the namelist_defaults_datm.xml
# file to the archival path of the case above in the form of: /glade/home/achive/$USER/$DATM_CPLHIST_CASE/cpl/hist
# NOTE: THIS WILL CHANGE THE PATH FOR ALL I1850SPINUPCN COMPSET CASES MADE AFTER THIS!
> $EDITOR ../../models/atm/datm/bld/namelist_files/namelist_defaults_datm.xml
> ./cesm_setup
# Now build and run as normal
> ./frcwmyBCN1850.build
> ./frcwmyBCN1850.submit
</screen>
</example>
<note>
<para>
We did this by editing the "namelist_defaults_datm.xml" which will change the settings for ALL future
I1850SPINUPCN cases you run. You could also do this by editing the path in the resulting streams text
files in the CaseDocs directory, and then create a "user_" streams file with the correct path. This would 
change the streams file JUST for this case. The steps do it this way are:
<screen width="99">
> ./preview_namelists
> cp CaseDocs/datm.streams.txt.CPLHIST3HrWx.Precip            user_datm.streams.txt.CPLHIST3HrWx.Precip
> cp CaseDocs/datm.streams.txt.CPLHIST3HrWx.Solar             user_datm.streams.txt.CPLHIST3HrWx.Solar
> cp CaseDocs/datm.streams.txt.CPLHIST3HrWx.nonSolarNonPrecip user_datm.streams.txt.CPLHIST3HrWx.nonSolarNonPrecip
# Change the &lt;fieldInfo&gt; field &lt;filePath&gt; to point to the correct directory i.e.: /glade/home/achive/$USER/$DATM_CPLHIST_CASE/cpl/hist
> $EDITOR user_datm.streams.txt.CPLHIST3HrWx.*
> ./preview_namelists
# Then make sure the CaseDocs/datm.streams.txt.CPLHIST3HrWx.* files have the correct path
</screen>
</para>
</note>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="DATM_CO2_TSERIES">
<title>Running stand-alone &clm; with transient historical &CO2;
concentration</title>
<para>
In this case you want to run a simulation with stand-alone &clm; responding
to changes in &CO2; for a historical period.
For this example, we will start with the "I_1850-2000_CN" compset that
has transient: land-use, Nitrogen and Aerosol deposition already. You could
also use another compset if you didn't want these other features to be transient.
In order to get &CO2; to be transient we need to add a new streams file
and add it to the list of streams in the user_nl_datm file. You also need
a &netcdf; datafile that datm can read that gives the variation. You could
supply your own file, but we have a standard file that is used by &cam; for this
and our example will make use of this file.
</para>
<note>
<para>
Most everything here has to do with changing datm rather than &clm;
to allow this to happen. As such the user that wishes to do this should
first become more familiar with datm and read the 
<ulink url="&cesmwebmodelrel;data8">&cesm; Data
Model User's Guide</ulink> especially as it pertains to the datm.
</para>
</note>
<warning>
<para>
This section documents the process for doing something that is non-standard.
There may be errors with the documentation and process, and you may have to do
some work before all of this works for you. If that is the case, we recommend
that you do further research into understanding the process and the files, as
well as understanding the datm and how it works. You may have to read documentation
found in the code for datm as well as "csm_share".
</para>
</warning>
<para>
The datm has "streams" files that have rough XML-like syntax and specify the
location and file to get data from, as well as information on the variable names
and the data locations of the grid points. The datm expects specific variable names
and the datm "maps" the expected variable names from the file to the names expected
by datm. The file we are working with here is a file with a single-point, that covers 
the entire globe (so the vertices go from -90 to 90 degrees in latitude and 0 to 360 
degrees in longitude). Since it's a single point it's a little easier to work with
than datasets that may be at a given horizontal resolution. The datm also expects
that variables will be in certain units, and only expects a limited number of 
variables so arbitrary fields can NOT be exchanged this way. However, the process
would be similar for datasets that do contain more than one point.
</para>
<para>
The three things that are needed: a domain file, a data file, and a streams text file.
The domain file is a CF-compliant &netcdf; file that has information
on the grid points (latitudes and longitudes for cell-centers and vertices, mask
, fraction, and areas). The datafile is a CF-compliant &netcdf; file with the data that 
will be mapped. The streams text file is the XML-like file that tells datm how to find
the files and how to map the variables datm knows about to the variable names on the
&netcdf; files. Note, that in our case the domain file and the data file are the same
file. In other cases, the domain file may be separate from the data file.
</para>
<para>
First we are going to create a case, and we will edit
the <filename>user_nl_datm</filename> so that we add a
&CO2; data stream in. There is a streams text file
available in <filename>models/lnd/clm/doc/UsersGuide/datm.streams.txt.co2</filename>,
that includes file with a &CO2; time-series from 1765 to 2007.
<example>
<title>Example Transient Simulation with Historical &CO2;</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case DATM_CO2_TSERIES -res f19_g16 -compset I_1850-2000_CN \
-mach yellowstone_intel
> cd DATM_CO2_TSERIES
# Set CCSM_BGC to CO2A so that CO2 will be passed from atmosphere to land
# Set CLM_CO2_TYPE to diagnostic so that the land will use the value sent from the atmosphere
> ./xmlchange CCSM_BGC=CO2A,CLM_CO2_TYPE=diagnostic
> ./cesm_setup
# Create the streams file for CO2
> cat &lt;&lt; EOF &gt;&gt; datm.streams.txt.co2tseries
&co2tseries;
EOF
# And copy it to the run directory
> cp datm.streams.txt.co2tseries $RUNDIR
# Run preview namelist so we have the namelist in CaseDocs
> ./preview_namelists
</screen>
</example>
The first thing we will do is to edit the user_nl_datm file to add 
a CO2 file stream in. To do this we will copy a <filename>user_nl_datm</filename>
in with the changes needed. The file <filename>addco2_user_nl_datm.user_nl</filename> is
in <filename>models/lnd/clm/doc/UsersGuide</filename> and looks like this...
<screen width="99">
&usernldatm_co2;
</screen>
You just copy this into your case directory. But, also compare it to the version
in <filename>CaseDocs</filename> to make sure the changes are just to add in
the new &CO2; stream. Check to see that filenames, and start, end and align
years are correct.
<screen width="99">
> cp ../../models/lnd/clm/doc/UsersGuide/addco2_user_nl_datm.user_nl user_nl_datm
> diff user_nl_datm CaseDocs/datm_atm_in
</screen>
Once, you've done that you can build and run your case normally.
</para>
<warning>
<para>
This procedure assumes you are using a <literal>I_1850-2000_CN</literal> compset out of the box, with
<envar>DATM_PRESAERO</envar> equal to <literal>trans_1850-2000</literal>. So it assumes standard
Qian atmosphere forcing, and transient prescribed aerosols from streams files. If your case changes
anything here your &usernldatm; file will need to be adjusted to work with it.
</para>
</warning>

<note>
<para>
The intent of the &usernldatm; is to adds an extra streams file for &CO2; to the end of the streams variable,
and other arrays associated with streams (adding mapalgo as a new array with bilinear for everything, but
the &CO2; file which should be "nn" for nearest neighbor). Other variables should be the same as the other
stream values.
</para>
</note>

<warning>
<para>
The streams file above is hard-coded for the path of the file on &ncar; computers. To use it on an outside
machine you'll need to edit the filepath in the streams file to point to the location where you have the file.
</para>
</warning>

<para>
After going through these steps, you will have a case where you have datm reading
in an extra streams text file that points to a data file with &CO2;
data on it that will send that data to the &clm;.
</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<!-- End of special cases chapter-->
